Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid & Racism; Records apap011
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Northeast Southern Africa Solidarity Network Papers, 1986-1990; 7; 0.13 cubic ft.
  Includes a mailing list, minutes for NESASN meetings (1988-1989), correspondence (1989-1990), and funding information such as a Peace Development Fund grant application and a copy of a 1986 article from the Grassroots Fund-raising Journal (1986-1989). Also includes information on fund-raising campaigns, lists of potential congressional supporters for sanctions bills, and lists of companies for potential boycotts circa 1988-1989. The series is divided by subject. Issues include boycotts of companies operating in South Africa, fund-raising, and lobbying for support of bills in Congress that would impose sanctions on South Africa. The NESASN minutes are brief, mentioning topics discussed at meetings with little elaboration. Issues covered in the 1988-89 minutes include the Shell Oil Company boycott, a bill in Congress for sanctions towards South Africa, the sending of delegations to frontline countries in southern Africa, fund-raising for the organization, and building a network to fight apartheid. The correspondence file contains letters from the Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism, the New Jersey Anti-Apartheid Mobilization Coalition, the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, and mailings from the NESASN.
  - Mailing List, 1988-1989 (Reel 5)
  - NESASN Minutes, 1988-1989 (Reel 5)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Reel 5)
  - Campaigns, 1988-1989 (Reel 5)
  - Funding, 1986; 1988-1989 (Reel 5)
- African National Congress Documents, 1989-1994; 8; 0.175 cubic ft.
  Includes reports, a newsletter, photocopies of newspaper articles, and ANC documents explaining how the South African government should be reconstructed. Included are constitutional principles and procedures for drawing up a constitution (1991-92), a declaration of intent issued at the Convention for a Democratic South Africa, a proposed economic policy for South Africa written by the ANC, lifting of sanctions against South Africa by European countries (1991), and ANC policy guidelines for a Democratic South Africa (1992). Also included is the August, 1993 issue of The Corporate Examiner which covers a July, 1993 meeting held by the South African Council of Churches where the topic of a "Code of Business Conduct" was discussed.
  - ANC Documents, 1989-1994 (Reel 5)
  - "Reconstruction and Development Programme", 1994 February 17 (Reel 5)
  - "Statement of Nelson Mandela", 1991 July 2-7 (Reel 5)
- Newsletter Editor's Files, 1984-1994; 9; 0.13 cubic ft.
  Seven folders from the files of CD-CAAR's secretary, Eileen Kawola. The subject files include press clippings, correspondence, information about the CD-CAAR Committee on Police and Racial Violence (1987-1989), the diary kept by Eileen Kawola on her 1992 trip to southern Africa which includes four photographs, and a brief history of Namibia circa 1984. The series also includes information about Mozambique gathered in preparation for the 1992 trip taken by Eileen Kawola and members of CD-CAAR to Mozambique as well as other countries in southern Africa, and information about educational programs conducted in the Albany schools after the trip. The file on Mozambique also includes information about financial support for Mozambique schools and churches. Included are copies of two CD-CAAR newsletters (October, 1991 and November 10, 1992), correspondence including letters of introduction, educational information about Mozambique, and the Albany Public School Teachers Association (APSTA) Bulletin dated October, 1992 containing a resolution in support of the Mozambique government.
  - Press Clippings on Mafasone Marobe and letter from Harry Rosenfeld, Albany Times Union, 1985-1986 (Reel 6)
  - CD-CAAR Committee on Police and Racial Violence, 1987-1989 (Reel 6)
  - Diary of trip to southern Africa with 4 photographs, 1992 (Reel 6)
  - CD-CAAR educational information on Namibia, 1984 (Reel 6)
  - Metroland article on southern Africa, 1992 (Reel 6)
  - Correspondence and AAA article, 1984 (Reel 6)
  - Mozambique, 1991-1994 (Reel 6)
- CD-CAAR Newsletters, 1983-1995; 10; 0.2 cubic ft. (Reel 6)
  A complete run of Capital District Coalition Against Apartheid and Racism newsletters edited by Eileen Kawola. The newsletters contain information about the activities and interests of CD-CAAR and events the organization sponsored. Many of the newsletters are in other parts of the CD-CAAR papers, although they are not represented there completely.
  - CD-CAAR Newsletters, 1983-1986 (Reel 6)
  - CD-CAAR Newsletters, 1987-1989 (Reel 6)
  - CD-CAAR Newsletters, 1991-1995 (Reel 6)